Vlček mss., 1915-1937 LMC 2515
Lilly Library
Vlček mss.
1915-1937
Lilly Library
Vlček, Jindra 1885-1968
LMC 2515
2 Boxes
The Vlček Mss., 1915-1937, consists of drawings, paintings, reproductions, and stamp designs of Czech artist Jindra Vlček, 1885-1968.
Access Restrictions
Access to this collection requires advance notice. Please contact the curator for additional information.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2004 (Michael Weintraub)
Biographical Note
Jindra Vlček, 1885-1968, was a Czech artist and World War I veteran. He was born in 1885 in Malá Skalice in what is now the Czech Republic. He graduated from the School of Applied Arts in Vienna and the Academy of Fine Arts in Prague. He spent two years, from 1906-1908, in the United States designing movie posters and working in advertising. Upon his return to Europe, he was imprisoned for evading military service. Czechs were at that time a part of the Austro-Hungarian empire and thus in 1914 he was sent to the Russian front in World War I to fight for Austria-Hungary. In October 1915 he was captured and joined the Czech Legion, a unit of Czech prisoners of war fighting for Russia as part of a bargain in which Russia promised Czech independence if they were victorious against the Austro-Hungarian empire. The Czech Legion became highly popular in the U.S. press, which in part helped to ensure that the Czechs achieved independence once World War I ended. From the 1920s through the 1950s, Vlček focused on his art, producing four designs for postage stamps commemorating battles in which the Czech Legion was involved, of which some originals are preserved in this collection. His other work includes paintings and charcoal sketches of landscapes, military scenes, and portraiture.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes drawings, stamp designs, paintings, reproductions, and correspondence of Czech artist Jindra Vlček. See the vertical file for item-level descriptions of nearly every item in the collection, including translations of any Czech text.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Artwork II. Photographs III. Miscellaneous.
Art; Postage stamp design; Vlček, Jindra, 1885-1968; Legie česká
- Artwork
  - Drawings & Paintings
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - Postcards 1915-1916 (Box 1)
    - 1916 (Box 2)
    - 1917 (Box 2)
    - 1918 (Box 2)
    - 1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920 (Box 2)
    - 1921 battlefield scene (Box 2)
    - 1925 battlefield scene (Box 2)
    - 1927 (Box 2)
  - Stamps
    - Battle of Zborov Stamps (1926-1937) (Box 1)
    - Battle of Vouziers pencil design (Box 2)
    - Battle of Vouziers watercolor design (Box 2)
    - Battle of Zborov design (1937) (Box 2)
    - Battle of Doss Alto design (1937) (Box 2)
  - Reproductions
    - N.D. or date illegible (Box 1)
    - 1915 (Box 1)
    - 1917 (Box 1)
    - 1918 (Box 1)
    - 1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920 (Box 1)
    - 1921 (Box 1)
    - 1923 (Box 1)
    - 1924 (Box 1)
    - 1925 (Box 1)
    - 1927 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Photomontage celebrating Vlček's 50th birthday (1935) (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Processing notes folder (Box 2)